So, it's taken us a
我们已经用了
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
lot of videos to get through
几节视频的内容
the neural network learning algorithm.
来介绍神经网络算法
In this video, what I'd like
在这段视频中
to do is try to
我想结合我们所讲的
put all the pieces together, to
所有这些内容
give a overall summary or
来做一个总体的回顾
a bigger picture view, of how
看看这些零散的内容
all the pieces fit together and
相互之间有怎样的联系
of the overall process of how
以及神经网络学习算法的
to implement a neural network learning algorithm.
总体实现过程
When training a neural network, the
当我们在训练一个神经网络时
first thing you need to do
我们要做的第一件事
is pick some network architecture
就是搭建网络的大体框架
and by architecture I just
这里我说的框架 意思是
mean connectivity pattern between the neurons.
神经元之间的连接模式
So, you know, we might choose
我们可能会从以下几种结构中选择
between say, a neural network
第一种神经网络的结构是
with three input units
包含三个输入单元
and five hidden units and
五个隐藏单元
four output units versus one
和四个输出单元
of 3, 5 hidden, 5
第二种结构是 三个输入单元作为输入层
hidden, 4 output and
两组五个隐藏单元作为隐藏层 四个输出单元的输出层
here are 3, 5,
然后第三种是3 5 5 5
5, 5 units in each
其中每个隐藏层包含五个单元
of three hidden layers and four
然后是四个输出单元
open units, and so these
这些就是可能选择的结构
choices of how many hidden
每一层可以选择
units in each layer
多少个隐藏单元
and how many hidden layers, those
以及可以选择多少个隐藏层
are architecture choices.
这些都是你构建时的选择
So, how do you make these choices?
那么我们该如何做出选择呢？
Well first, the number
首先 我们知道
of input units well that's pretty well defined.
我们已经定义了输入单元的数量
And once you decides on the fix
一旦你确定了特征集x
set of features x the
对应的输入单元数目
number of input units will just be, you know, the
也就确定了
dimension of your features x(i)
也就是等于特征x的维度
would be determined by that.
输入单元数目将会由此确定
And if you are doing multiclass
如果你正在进行
classifications the number of
多类别分类
output of this will be
那么输出层的单元数目
determined by the number
将会由你分类问题中
of classes in your classification problem.
所要区分的类别个数确定
And just a reminder if you have
值得提醒的是
a multiclass classification where y
如果你的多元分类问题
takes on say values between
y的取值范围
1 and 10, so that
是在1到10之间
you have ten possible classes.
那么你就有10个可能的分类
Then remember to right, your
别忘了把你的y
output y as these were the vectors.
重新写成向量的形式
So instead of clause one, you
所以现在我们的y不是一个数了
recode it as a vector
我们重新把y写成
like that, or for
这种形式的向量
the second class you recode it as a vector like that.
第二个分类我们可以写成这样的向量
So if one of these
所以 比如说
apples takes on
如果要表达
the fifth class, you know, y equals 5, then
第五个分类 也就是说y等于5
what you're showing to your neural
那么在你的神经网络中
network is not actually a value
就不能直接用
of y equals 5, instead here
数值5来表达
at the upper layer which would
因为这里的输出层
have ten output units, you
有十个输出单元
will instead feed to the
你应该用一个向量
vector which you know
来表示
with one in the fifth
这个向量的第五个位置值是1
position and a bunch of zeros down here.
其它的都是0
So the choice of number
所以对于输入单元
of input units and number of output units
和输出单元数目的选择
is maybe somewhat reasonably straightforward.
还是比较容易理解的
And as for the number
那么对于隐藏层
of hidden units and the
单元的个数
number of hidden layers, a
以及隐藏层的数目
reasonable default is to
我们有一个默认的规则
use a single hidden layer
那就是只使用单个隐藏层
and so this type of
所以最左边所示的
neural network shown on the left with
这种只有一个隐藏层的神经网络
just one hidden layer is probably the most common.
一般来说是最普遍的
Or if you use more
或者如果你使用
than one hidden layer, again the
不止一个隐藏层的话
reasonable default will be to
同样我们也有一个默认规则
have the same number of
那就是每一个隐藏层
hidden units in every single layer.
通常都应有相同的单元数
So here we have two
所以对于这个结构
hidden layers and each
我们有两个隐藏层
of these hidden layers have the
每个隐藏层都有相同的单元数
same number five of hidden
都是5个隐藏单元
units and here we have, you know,
这里也是一样
three hidden layers and
我们有三个隐藏层
each of them has the same
每个隐藏层有相同的单元数
number, that is five hidden units.
都是5个隐藏单元
Rather than doing this sort
但实际上通常来说
of network architecture on the left would be a perfect ably reasonable default.
左边这个结构是较为合理的默认结构
And as for the number
而对于隐藏单元的个数
of hidden units - usually, the
通常情况下
more hidden units the better;
隐藏单元越多越好
it's just that if you have
不过 我们需要注意的是
a lot of hidden units, it
如果有大量隐藏单元
can become more computationally expensive, but
计算量一般会比较大
very often, having more hidden units is a good thing.
当然 一般来说隐藏单元还是越多越好
And usually the number of hidden
并且一般来说 每个隐藏层
units in each layer will be maybe
所包含的单元数量
comparable to the dimension
还应该和输入x
of x, comparable to the
的维度相匹配
number of features, or it could
也要和特征的数目匹配
be any where from same number
可能隐藏单元的数目
of hidden units of input features to
和输入特征的数量相同
maybe so that three or four times of that.
或者是它的二倍 或者三倍 四倍
So having the number of hidden units is comparable.
因此 隐藏单元的数目需要和其他参数相匹配
You know, several times, or
一般来说
some what bigger than the number
隐藏单元的数目取为稍大于
of input features is often
输入特征数目
a useful thing to do So,
都是可以接受的
hopefully this gives you one
希望这些能够给你
reasonable set of default choices
在选择神经网络结构时
for neural architecture and and
提供一些有用的建议和选择的参考
if you follow these guidelines, you
如果你遵循了这些建议
will probably get something that works
你一般会得到比较好的模型结构
well, but in a
但是
later set of videos where
在以后的一系列视频中
I will talk specifically about
特别是在我谈到
advice for how to apply
学习算法的应用时
algorithms, I will actually
我还会更详细地介绍
say a lot more about how to choose a neural network architecture.
如何选择神经网络的结构
Or actually have quite
后面的视频中
a lot I want to
我还会着重介绍
say later to make good choices
怎样正确地选择隐藏层的个数
for the number of hidden units, the number of hidden layers, and so on.
以及隐藏单元的数目 等等
Next, here's what we
下面我们就来具体介绍
need to implement in order to
如何实现神经网络的
trade in neural network, there are
训练过程
actually six steps that I
这里一共有六个步骤
have; I have four on this
这页幻灯片中罗列了前四步
slide and two more steps
剩下的两步
on the next slide.
放在下一张幻灯片中
First step is to set up the neural
首先 第一步是构建一个
network and to randomly
神经网络
initialize the values of the weights.
然后随机初始化权值
And we usually initialize the
通常我们把权值
weights to small values near zero.
初始化为很小的值 接近于零
Then we implement forward propagation
然后我们执行前向传播算法
so that we can input
也就是 对于该神经网络的
any excellent neural network and
任意一个输入x(i)
compute h of x which is this
计算出对应的h(x)值
output vector of the y values.
也就是一个输出值y的向量
We then also implement code to
接下来我们通过代码
compute this cost function j of theta.
计算出代价函数J(θ)
And next we implement
然后我们执行
back-prop, or the back-propagation
反向传播算法
algorithm, to compute these
来算出这些偏导数 或偏微分项
partial derivatives terms, partial
也就是
derivatives of j of theta
J(θ)关于参数θ的偏微分
with respect to the parameters. Concretely, to implement back prop.
具体来说
Usually we will do that
我们要对所有训练集数据
with a fore loop over the training examples.
使用一个for循环进行遍历
Some of you may have heard of
可能有部分同学之前听说过
advanced, and frankly very
一些比较先进的分解方法
advanced factorization methods where you
可能不需要像这里一样使用
don't have a four-loop over
for循环来对所有
the m-training examples, that the
m个训练样本进行遍历
first time you're implementing back prop
但是 这是你第一次进行反向传播算法
there should almost certainly the four
所以我建议你最好还是
loop in your code,
使用一个for循环来完成程序
where you're iterating over the examples,
对每一个训练样本进行迭代
you know, x1, y1, then so
从x(1) y(1)开始
you do forward prop and
我们对第一个样本进行
back prop on the first
前向传播运算和反向传播运算
example, and then in
然后在第二次循环中
the second iteration of the
同样地对第二个样本
four-loop, you do forward propagation
执行前向传播和反向传播算法
and back propagation on the second example, and so on.
以此类推
Until you get through the final example.
直到最后一个样本
So there should be
因此 在你第一次做反向传播的时候
a four-loop in your implementation
你还是应该用这样的for循环
of back prop, at least the first time implementing it.
来实现这个过程
And then there are frankly
其实实际上
somewhat complicated ways to do
有复杂的方法可以实现
this without a four-loop, but
并不一定要使用for循环
I definitely do not recommend
但我非常不推荐
trying to do that much more
在第一次实现反向传播算法的时候
complicated version the first time you try to implement back prop.
使用更复杂更高级的方法
So concretely, we have a
所以具体来讲 我们对所有的
four-loop over my m-training examples
m个训练样本上使用了for循环遍历
and inside the four-loop we're
在这个for循环里
going to perform fore prop
我们对每个样本执行
and back prop using just this one example.
前向和反向算法
And what that means is that
具体来说就是
we're going to take x(i), and
我们把x(i)
feed that to my input layer,
传到输入层
perform forward-prop, perform back-prop
然后执行前向传播和反向传播
and that will if all of
这样我们就能得到
these activations and all of
该神经网络中
these delta terms for all
每一层中每一个单元对应的
of the layers of all my
所有这些激励值a(l)
units in the neural
和delta项
network then still
接下来
inside this four-loop, let
还是在for循环中
me draw some curly braces
让我画一个大括号
just to show the scope with
来标明这个
the four-loop, this is in
for循环的范围
octave code of course, but it's more a sequence Java
当然这些是octave的代码
code, and a four-loop encompasses all this.
括号里是for循环的循环体
We're going to compute those delta
我们要计算出这些delta值
terms, which are is the formula that we gave earlier.
也就是用我们之前给出的公式
Plus, you know, delta l plus one times
加上 delta(l+1)
a, l transpose of the code.
a(l)的转置矩阵
And then finally, outside the
最后 外面的部分
having computed these delta
计算出的这些delta值
terms, these accumulation terms, we
这些累加项
would then have some other
我们将用别的程序
code and then that will
来计算出
allow us to compute these partial derivative terms.
这些偏导数项
Right and these partial derivative
那么这些偏导数项
terms have to take
也应该考虑使用
into account the regularization term lambda as well.
正则化项lambda值
And so, those formulas were given in the earlier video.
这些公式在前面的视频中已经给出
So, how do you done that
那么 搞定所有这些内容
you now hopefully have code to
现在你就应该已经得到了
compute these partial derivative terms.
计算这些偏导数项的程序了
Next is step five, what I
下面就是第五步了
do is then use gradient
我要做的就是使用梯度检查
checking to compare these partial
来比较这些
derivative terms that were computed. So, I've
已经计算得到的偏导数项
compared the versions computed using
把用反向传播算法
back propagation versus the
得到的偏导数值
partial derivatives computed using the numerical
与用数值方法得到的
estimates as using numerical estimates of the derivatives.
估计值进行比较
So, I do gradient checking to make
因此 通过进行梯度检查来
sure that both of these give you very similar values.
确保两种方法得到基本接近的两个值
Having done gradient checking just now reassures
通过梯度检查我们能确保
us that our implementation of back
我们的反向传播算法
propagation is correct, and is
得到的结果是正确的
then very important that we disable
但必须要说明的一点是
gradient checking, because the gradient
我们需要去掉梯度检查的代码
checking code is computationally very slow.
因为梯度检查的计算非常慢
And finally, we then
最后 我们就可以
use an optimization algorithm such
使用一个最优化算法
as gradient descent, or one of
比如说梯度下降算法
the advanced optimization methods such
或者说是更加高级的优化方法
as LB of GS, contract gradient has
比如说BFGS算法 共轭梯度法
embodied into fminunc or other  optimization methods.
或者其他一些已经内置到fminunc函数中的方法
We use these together with
将所有这些优化方法
back propagation, so back
和反向传播算法相结合
propagation is the thing
这样我们就能计算出
that computes these partial derivatives for us.
这些偏导数项的值
And so, we know how to
到现在 我们已经知道了
compute the cost function, we know
如何去计算代价函数
how to compute the partial derivatives using
我们知道了如何使用
back propagation, so we
反向传播算法来计算偏导数
can use one of these optimization methods
那么 我们就能使用某个最优化方法
to try to minimize j of
来最小化关于theta的函数值
theta as a function of the parameters theta.
代价函数J(θ)
And by the way, for
另外顺便提一下
neural networks, this cost function
对于神经网络 代价函数
j of theta is non-convex,
J(θ)是一个非凸函数
or is not convex and so
就是说不是凸函数
it can theoretically be susceptible
因此理论上是能够停留在
to local minima, and in
局部最小值的位置
fact algorithms like gradient descent and
实际上 梯度下降算法
the advance optimization methods can,
和其他一些高级优化方法
in theory, get stuck in local
理论上都能收敛于局部最小值
optima, but it turns out
但一般来讲
that in practice this is
这个问题其实
not usually a huge problem
并不是什么要紧的事
and even though we can't guarantee
尽管我们不能保证
that these algorithms will find a
这些优化算法一定会得到
global optimum, usually algorithms like
全局最优值 但通常来讲
gradient descent will do a
像梯度下降这类的算法
very good job minimizing this
在最小化代价函数
cost function j of
J(θ)的过程中
theta and get a
还是表现得很不错的
very good local minimum, even
通常能够得到一个很小的局部最小值
if it doesn't get to the global optimum.
尽管这可能不一定是全局最优值
Finally, gradient descents for
最后 梯度下降算法
a neural network might still seem a little bit magical.
似乎对于神经网络来说还是比较神秘
So, let me just show one
希望下面这幅图
more figure to try to get
能让你对梯度下降法在神经网络中的应用
that intuition about what gradient descent for a neural network is doing.
产生一个更直观的理解
This was actually similar to the
这实际上有点类似
figure that I was using earlier to explain gradient descent.
我们早先时候解释梯度下降时的思路
So, we have some cost
我们有某个代价函数
function, and we have
并且在我们的神经网络中
a number of parameters in our neural network. Right
有一系列参数值
here I've just written down two of the parameter values.
这里我只写下了两个参数值
In reality, of course, in
当然实际上
the neural network, we can have lots of parameters with these.
在神经网络里 我们可以有很多的参数值
Theta one, theta two--all of these are matrices, right?
theta1 theta2 等等 所有的这些都是矩阵 是吧
So we can have very high dimensional
因此我们参数的维度就会很高了
parameters but because of
由于绘图所限 我们不能绘出
the limitations the source of
更高维度情况的图像
parts we can draw. I'm pretending
所以这里我们假设
that we have only two parameters in this neural network.
这个神经网络中只有两个参数值
Although obviously we have a lot more in practice.
实际上应该有更多参数
Now, this cost function j of
那么 代价函数J(θ)
theta measures how well
度量的就是这个神经网络
the neural network fits the training data.
对训练数据的拟合情况
So, if you take a point
所以 如果你取某个参数
like this one, down here,
比如说这个 下面这点
that's a point where j
在这个点上 J(θ)
of theta is pretty low,
的值是非常小的
and so this corresponds to a setting of the parameters.
这一点的位置所对应的
There's a setting of the parameters
参数theta的情况是
theta, where, you know, for most
对于大部分
of the training examples, the output
的训练集数据
of my hypothesis, that may
我的假设函数的输出
be pretty close to y(i)
会非常接近于y(i)
and if this is
那么如果是这样的话
true than that's what causes my cost function to be pretty low.
那么我们的代价函数值就会很小
Whereas in contrast, if you were
而反过来 如果我们
to take a value like that, a
取这个值
point like that corresponds to,
也就是这个点对应的值
where for many training examples,
那么对于大部分的训练集样本
the output of my neural
该神经网络的输出
network is far from
应该是远离
the actual value y(i)
y(i)的实际值的
that was observed in the training set.
也就是我们在训练集观测到的输出值
So points like this on the
因此 像这样的点
line correspond to where the
右边的这个点
hypothesis, where the neural
对应的假设就是
network is outputting values
神经网络的输出值
on the training set that are
在这个训练集上的测试值
far from y(i). So, it's not
应该是远离y(i)的
fitting the training set well, whereas
因此这一点对应着对训练集拟合得不好的情况
points like this with low
而像这些点
values of the cost function corresponds
代价函数值很小的点
to where j of theta
对应的J(θ)值
is low, and therefore corresponds
是很小的 因此对应的是
to where the neural network happens
神经网络对训练集数据
to be fitting my training set
拟合得比较好的情况
well, because I mean this is what's
我想表达的是 如果是这种情况的话
needed to be true in order for j of theta to be small.
那么J(θ)的值应该是比较小的
So what gradient descent does is
因此梯度下降算法的原理是
we'll start from some random
我们从某个随机的
initial point like that
初始点开始 比如这一点
one over there, and it will repeatedly go downhill.
它将会不停的往下下降
And so what back propagation is
那么反向传播算法
doing is computing the direction
的目的就是算出
of the gradient, and what
梯度下降的方向
gradient descent is doing is
而梯度下降的过程
it's taking little steps downhill
就是沿着这个方向
until hopefully it gets to,
一点点的下降 一直到我们希望得到的点
in this case, a pretty good local optimum.
在这里我们希望找到的就是局部最优点
So, when you implement back
所以 当你在执行反向传播算法
propagation and use gradient
并且使用梯度下降
descent or one of the
或者其他别的什么
advanced optimization methods, this picture
更高级的优化方法时
sort of explains what the algorithm is doing.
这幅图片很好地帮你解释了基本的原理
It's trying to find a value
也就是 试图找到某个最优的参数值
of the parameters where the
这个值使得
output values in the neural
我们神经网络的输出值
network closely matches the
与y(i)的实际值
values of the y(i)'s
也就是训练集的输出观测值
observed in your training set.
尽可能的接近
So, hopefully this gives you
希望这节课的内容能让你对
a better sense of how
这些零散的神经网络知识
the many different pieces of
如何有机地结合起来
neural network learning fit together.
能有一个更直观的认识
In case even after this video, in
也许看完这段视频
case you still feel like there
你可能还是觉得
are, like, a lot of different pieces
有许多的细节
and it's not entirely clear what
不能完全明白
some of them do or how all
为什么这么做 或者说是这些是如何
of these pieces come together, that's actually okay.
联系在一起的 没关系
Neural network learning and back propagation is a complicated algorithm.
神经网络和反向传播算法本身就是非常复杂的算法
And even though I've seen
尽管我已经完全理解了
the math behind back propagation
反向传播算法背后的数学原理
for many years and I've used
尽管我使用反向传播已经很多年了
back propagation, I think very
我认为 这么多年的使用还算是成功的
successfully, for many years, even
但尽管如此
today I still feel like I
到现在我还是觉得
don't always have a great
我自己也并不是总能
grasp of exactly what back propagation is doing sometimes.
很好地理解反向传播到底在做什么
And what the optimization process
以及最优化过程是如何
looks like of minimizing j if theta.
使J(θ)值达到最小值的
Much this is a much harder algorithm
因为这本身的确是一个很难的算法
to feel like I have a
很难让你感觉到
much less good handle on
自己已经完全理解
exactly what this is doing
它不像线性回归
compared to say, linear regression or logistic regression.
或者逻辑回归那样
Which were mathematically and conceptually
数学上和概念上都很简单
much simpler and much cleaner algorithms.
反向传播算法不是那样的直观
But so in case if you feel the
如果你也有同感
same way, you know, that's actually perfectly
那么完全不必担心
okay, but if you
但如果你自己动手
do implement back propagation, hopefully
完成一次反向传播算法
what you find is that this
你一定会发现
is one of the most powerful
这的确是一个很强大的
learning algorithms and if you
学习算法 如果你
implement this algorithm, implement back propagation,
执行一下这个算法 执行反向传播
implement one of these optimization
执行其中的优化方法
methods, you find that
你一定会发现
back propagation will be able
反向传播算法能够很好的
to fit very complex, powerful, non-linear
让更复杂 维度更大的 非线性的
functions to your data,
函数模型跟你的数据很好地拟合
and this is one of the
因此它的确是一种
most effective learning algorithms we have today.
最为高效的学习算法